

SOUMADEEP BASU

Richardson, Texas, United States 75080 soumadeepbasu98@gmail.com / 4699435336

SUMMARY

A passionate, hardworking and creative developer with a background in Full Stack Development, Machine Learning and Cloud Technologies.

I may not always be the smartest in the room, but I am always the one who is working thrice as hard. Whether it is research, development, leadership or consulting, if the goal is something that I believe in, there are few things that can stop me from getting there:)

SKILLS

Languages

- Java
- Python
- C++
- MATLAB
- Node
- Angular
- React
- Terraform
- SQL

Platforms

Azure

- MongoDB/PostgreSQL
- Heroku
- Databricks
- Jenkins
- Git
- Apache Spark/Hadoop

Libraries

- OpenCV
- Numpy
- Pandas
- Sklearn

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Master of Science: Computer Science (Intelligent Systems)

The University of Texas At Dallas - Richardson, TX

CGPA: 3.67

Bachelor of Science: Computer Science And Engineering

RV College of Engineering - Bangalore

CGPA: 8.54

Expected in 05/2023

05/2020

EXPERIENCE

Associate Software Developer / Optum Global Solutions, UHG - Bangalore, Karnataka

07/2020 - 06/2021

- Worked on Azure Devops and Cloud capabilities to migrate existing services onto an Azure managed platform
- Designed and maintained API's and Services extensively using JAVA, Spring & Maven
- Built process flow automation with terraform and python Azure Functions
- Database design, management and migration with Mongo DB and PostgreSQL
- Front End Development using NodeJs and Angular

- Infrastructure design and analysis for migrating existing IVR architecture to suit the needs of conversational AI
- Dataset design for NLP model
- NLP model development responsible for analyzing voice input over telephonic lines
- Converting client expectations into technological designs and upholding quality standards

Al Developer Intern / Wipro - Bangalore, Karnataka

06/2018 - 07/2018

- Worked on developing a reinforcement learning model for existing customer facing chatbot
- Dataset design and performance metrics for the same

Hand Sign Recognition for Domestic Abuse / Personal Project

02/2021 - 03/2021

 Used the mediapipe library along with OpenCV, python and tensorflow to create a model that could effectively recognize the universal sign for abuse on live video

Hadoop and Scala Implementations / Personal Project

03/2022 - 04/2022

- Made use of Apache Hadoop and Spark to perform big data analytics on large volumes of data.
- Streamlined process flows and optimized time and space complexities.

Crypto Trading Website / Personal Project

06/2021 - 08/2021

- Built website using Angular, Flask, CSS and Bootstrap
- Hosted the site on Heroku
- Prioritized user experience and gave cadence to asthetic design

 	_		_	
 NI.	വ	 ^	\boldsymbol{c}	FS

English:	Bengali:
Native/ Bilingual	Native/ Bilingual
Hindi:	Kannada:
Native/ Bilingual	Full Professional

PUBLICATIONS

- Conference Reasonably Intelligent Mirror 12/2020 Iyer, S. R., Basu, S., Yadav, S., Vijayanand, V. M., & Badrinath, K. (2018, December). Reasonably Intelligent Mirror. In 2018 3rd International Conference on Computational Systems and Information Technology for Sustainable Solutions (CSITSS) (pp. 302-306). IEEE.
- Journal Publication Study of the Effect of AI on Industries and Employment 05/2020 https://irjet.net/archives/V7/i4/IRJET-V7I41200.pdf Basu, S., Nasreen, A.(2020, May). Study of the Effect of AI on Industries and Employment. In International Research Journal of Engineering and Technology (IRJET), Vol. 7, No. 4, (pp. 6366-6379).

REACH ME @

- https://www.linkedin.com/in/SoumadeepBasu98
- https://github.com/Soumadeep-Basu